<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- This is an automatically generated file. -->
<Chapter Label="Chapter_Semi6">
<Heading>Semi6</Heading>

 The <B>Semirings</B> package provides a means of encoding and decoding
 into a format called <B>Semi6</B>, inspired by the <B>graph6</B> format.
<P/>
 <B>Semi6</B> encodes a semiring <Math>S = (A,M)</Math> of order <Math>n</Math> (two <Math>n \times n</Math>
 Cayley tables) as one short ASCII string.
<P/>
 The first byte is <Math>n + 63</Math>, exactly as in <B>graph6</B>.
 The payload is a bit-stream: first the upper triangle (diagonal included)
 of the symmetric table <Math>A</Math>, then the full table <Math>M</Math>. Each entry is stored
 in <Math>b = \lceil{\log_2 n\rceil}</Math> bits, most-significant bit first.
 Zero-bits are used for padding until the length is a multiple of 6.
 The stream is then divided into 6-bit blocks, each block has 63 added,
 and the resulting bytes (ASCII 63–126) are concatenated.
 Thus a semiring becomes one short, string that is identical
 in spirit to <B>graph6</B>, but with a variable‐width 
 per-entry field instead of the single edge-bit used for graphs.
 That is to say, the <Math>b=1</Math> case effectively reduces to the
 <B>graph6</B> format (with an additional square table).
<P/>
 The order of the semiring must be between 1 and 63, inclusive.
<Section Label="Chapter_Semi6_Section_Encoding">
<Heading>Encoding</Heading>

<ManSection>
  <Func Arg="S" Name="Semi6String" />
 <Returns>a string
</Returns>
 <Description>
The function <C>Semi6String</C> encodes a semiring
 <A>S</A> into a string in the Semi6 format.
 </Description>
</ManSection>


<ManSection>
  <Func Arg="f, srs, [mode]" Name="Semi6Encode" />
 <Description>
If <A>srs</A> is a semiring or list of semirings
 (as pairs of Cayley tables) and <A>f</A> is a string containing
 the name of a file or an IO file object, <C>Semi6Encode</C> writes
 the semirings to the file represented by <A>f</A> in the Semi6 format.
<P/>
 The optional argument <A>mode</A> can be either <C>"w"</C> or <C>"a"</C>
 (default), which determines the mode in which the file is opened for writing.
 </Description>
</ManSection>


</Section>


<Section Label="Chapter_Semi6_Section_Decoding">
<Heading>Decoding</Heading>

<ManSection>
  <Func Arg="str" Name="SemiringFromSemi6String" />
 <Returns>a list of Cayley tables
</Returns>
 <Description>
This function takes a string <A>str</A> in the Semi6 format
 representing a semiring and returns that semiring as a pair of
 Cayley tables.
 </Description>
</ManSection>


<ManSection>
  <Func Arg="f, [n]" Name="Semi6Decode" />
 <Returns>a list of Cayley tables, or a list of pairs of  Cayley tables
</Returns>
 <Description>
If <A>f</A> is a string containing the name of a file containing
 encoded semirings or an IO file object, then <C>Semi6Decode</C>
 returns the semirings
 encoded in the file as a list of pairs of Cayley tables.
<P/>
 If the optional argument <A>n</A> is given, then <C>Semi6Decode</C>
 returns the <A>n</A>th semiring encoded in the file as a pair of
 Cayley tables.
 </Description>
</ManSection>


</Section>


</Chapter>

